foreign
[Music]
table number 39 I am Gonzalo Lira and I
am joined by my two guests Larry Johnson
and John kiriaku and we are going to
talk about all things intelligence you
know to understand the world and I've
drawn these two gentlemen to discuss a
lot of stuff about the intelligence
community and I'm particularly
interested in focusing on the failures
unfortunately of the intelligence
community so far and also something else
that it's inevitable you know the
creeping uh uh sense that the alphabet
agencies are kind of like taking over
the public discourse in the west and
controlling what people find out about
which is deeply disturbing I mean it's
really third world Banana Republic kind
of stuff so anyway first of all let me
welcome my guest Larry Johnson Larry
how's it going man I am well thank you
for having me I'll from the time pop is
a live camera when I'm not talking that
way I won't be robotic but when I talk
I'll go back to the to the picture
it's a handsome picture you look great
you know I mean like uh me I I look at
me live man I don't look so good so yeah
you look great thank you so much Larry
for joining us it's always a pleasure
you know he's a Larry's a repeated guest
for those of you who are new to the show
and it's just a delight and a treat to
have him on John kiriaku how's it going
my friend hey doing well thanks thanks
so much for inviting me
oh it's my pleasure and by the way uh to
both my for both my guests you'll see in
the in the description of the video as
well as a pin comment links to the work
of these two gentlemen you can find
Larry at sonar21.com and you can find
John at uh substack his substack link is
uh John kiriaku all one
word.substack.com and uh they write
great stuff it's the stuff that you have
to read and John I'm going to start with
you you were telling me before the show
started about something the CIA is doing
something naughty you know so they're
going to be on the naughty list for well
for next visit they're going to be on
the naughty list yes the CIA announced
get this two years ago that they were
opening a new lab but when they
announced it nobody paid any attention
nobody covered it and just in the last
week or two it started making the rounds
on social media so they've opened this
lab which they say is going to be it's
called CIA lab ABS plural and it's part
of the US government's network of 300
Labs that you know are set up all around
the world God knows what they're going
to do but they say you know they're
they're gonna develop Cutting Edge
technology to keep the country safe and
they're going to be a leader in
artificial intelligence and in Quantum
Computing and biotechnology
etc etc there was a statement by the
cia's deputy director for Science and
Technology that this is going to be so
great for everybody and um it's it's
best for Science and and everybody's
going to be happy and everybody is going
to be safer because
nonsense guitars
exactly and so
none of that's true none of that's true
and and let's begin at the beginning uh
the truth is that the CIA has had labs
for well over a half a century
and those labs sorry but these are
because they're nowadays they use the
lab for all kinds of stuff these are
biomedical research Labs correct exactly
correct and what the hell are they
developing in this particular new CIA
lab that they're talking well the new
CIA lab they won't tell us
yeah we're supposed to take their word
for it that it's it's all for the for
the betterment of mankind yeah of course
because the CIA has such a smaller track
record in that regard exactly okay but
you know they talk in these generalities
like Ai and I say in this piece that I
just did for Consortium news it was
published this morning and I put it on
substack
I say on my very first day at the CIA uh
my boss my new boss was taking me to
lunch I didn't know where the cafeteria
was so I was walking with him to go to
lunch and I noticed as we were passing a
window I noticed some movement uh
outside the window and it was this this
thing that looks like a like a short
round robot and it was it was mowing the
lawn and I said oh what is that that
looks like a robot and my boss said oh
uh you know here at the CIA we have a
lot of labs and scientific facilities
and we developed these new technologies
and we developed this thing and we just
don't know what to do with it so they
trained it to mow the lawn well it was
the predecessor of the Roomba which
nobody knows was actually CIA uh it was
a CIA invention using taxpayer money
that now vacuums the floor of your house
right okay that's not what we're talking
about here okay this isn't like DARPA
that's that's going to do something good
for Humanity right right but what the
CIA has done over the years the most
obvious example uh is something called
MK Ultra which I think most Americans
are familiar with where they uh they
dosed unwitting Americans including
their own employees and contractors with
LSD just to see how they would react now
the the purpose of of doing that at the
time was well we wanted to
um we wanted to see if the LSD was a
viable weapon that we could use against
the Soviet Union or against Soviet Bloc
countries because what we really wanted
to see is if we dosed people with LSD
would they speak freely about classified
information that they had access to
um it was a disaster and we knew that it
was a disaster so it sort of morphed
into experimentation in mind control
they got away from LSD and started using
all different kinds of drugs I list
several of them in the piece drugs most
of us have never heard of I I never
heard of them you know except for
mescaline which they also used in
experimentation but there were there
were other programs at other Labs things
like MK tickwit MK Ultra I mentioned a
second ago MK often uh project midnight
something or other uh they would do
things like the CIA yeah it does all
kinds of crazy ass stuff but like
specifically this Revelation now that's
coming out now what's the upshot I mean
it it what's the thing that that has you
like whoa whoa Nelly what's going on
here what's the thing that that sparked
your your your your antenna if you will
it's the cia's track record you know we
we hear so much already about what DARPA
is doing uh coming up with
um for example lasers that we would use
on the battlefield to Blind uh fighters
on the other side that's actually a war
crime you can't do that it's a violation
of international law that hasn't stopped
us from developing the weapons so rather
than to shoot people or kill them we we
fire lasers at them and um and they go
blind permanently okay uh well
what's to stop the CIA from
participating in something like that
there's no law no rule there's no
there's no announcement from the
Congressional oversight committees that
they can't do something like that and
when they come right out and say that
they're now involved in artificial
intelligence and biotechnology and
working with with these other
governmental agencies like DARPA and NSA
we're working with
um with classified defense contractors
in this new lab that has no civilian
oversight no public oversight and only
the the big four of the two
congressional committees the chairman
and vice chairman of the House and
Senate committees have access to the
information
autonomous lab that's going to develop
all kinds of crazy ass stuff and
nobody's going to know what it is or how
much money is being spent on it
you know I want to pull in Larry uh for
this I mean
what see the thing that has me like
freaked out at this point to tell you
the truth is the fact that a lot of the
alphabet a agencies are going had have
been shown now to be manipulating social
media platforms and directly
participating we we know about the FBI
but I'm assuming the CIA has something
analogous to what the FBI was doing
insofar as propaganda efforts and so
forth
can we even say Larry at this point that
we have like a democracy I mean can we
say that the CIA the intelligence
community in the United States is really
just part of a a political a
socio-political academic Financial class
that does not care about the people
anymore I mean help me out here yeah no
that yeah the short answer is yes before
we do that I I had a question for John
so were you going to lunch in the
unclass or the class classified
cafeteria yeah that's a good that's a
good question
um it was in the classified cafeteria oh
okay CIA used to have two different
cafeterias one for classified
conversations and one for unclassified
conversations
um you had to take people like from the
state department or from outside to the
unclassified cafeteria which was really
tiny and not very nice they ended up
turning that into an event space and now
everybody has to go to the classified
cafeteria you know listen to you guys
talk about this you know it's like two
guys from the same High School talking
about the cafeteria there you know oh
yeah the food was garbage and remember
you know Mrs Smith who who made the best
cupcakes or whatever I mean it sounds
like that but anyway
can I add something I don't mean to get
too far afield sure but you know
part of or one of the problems of the
cafeteria was uh on the morning that
Mary malkansi opened fire at the red
light in front of the CIA and and killed
two CIA employees and wounded I think it
was six others uh you know the CIA kind
of went crazy trying to uh find him and
to to track down his background it turns
out that his roommate
worked for Dunkin Donuts and his
roommate had access to the CIA to
deliver Donuts every day to the CIA
cafeteria
okay how did something like that happen
like is everybody asleep at the switch
well that's a good question that you can
ask sorry sorry I I changed places and I
know I look like the Prince of Darkness
now uh because I have like this little
Terrace in my apartment where I can like
uh smoke because I'm you know I'm in a
war zone man I mean give me something
you know but anyway no
um about that about the the failures to
anticipate like obvious things because
look this is the thing that pisses me
off about the intelligence uh uh
communities in the west that they do not
seem to be able to anticipate what is
obvious to everybody else of things that
are coming and reactions that are going
to come because of certain actions done
by Western governments why why are the
intelligence communities all failing in
the west why are they unable to provide
intelligent analysis that can actually
help the democratic nations of the West
make wise decisions I'm throwing it out
to both of you yeah the the simple
answers it's a bureaucracy and the
bureaucracy with all of the bureaucratic
incentives which are run counter to the
sort of what I'll call the Curiosity
intellectual incentives that one would
associate with in good intelligence
analysis so
and let me go back to your first
question about the the influence on
Twitter this really isn't new remember
that there was an age when the CIA was
infiltrating the regular media with
human beings and doing it the
old-fashioned way when the in the era
when they're using typewriters so this
is not new it's it's just it's a
continuation it's an expansion but the
the bureaucratic element that's out
there at CIA and I'll be curious to see
what John if John's experience was the
same as mine
the Hollywood image the popular
literature image is of CIA with these
highly intelligent people and with the
enormous background and experience and
depth and morality Well Jack Ryan he's
supposed to be the poster boy for this
yeah yeah
um
setting the morality issues aside uh I
go back to my experience when I walked
into the Middle America Caribbean
division
and this fall of 1986
and I was in the Central American Branch
so right right away I'm giving you the
bureaucratic structure so you have this
branch and then you have a division and
then above or an office the Middle
America Caribbean Division and then in
the office of Africa Latin American
Affairs so it's you know it's very
hierarchical
and so in in my office there was a
Honduras analyst me
there was an analyst for Panama there
were uh two analysts three working on
Salvador because Salvador was a big
priority for the United States uh
Nicaragua had its own Branch where John
and John and I have a mutual friend
Fulton who was the uh the chief analyst
over there and out of all of these
analysts here we are in Central America
branch I was the only one that spoke
Spanish and spoke it at a level four I
was the only one that had actually lived
in Central America
so you've got people that are supposed
to have this expertise in depth and they
don't they come in and they get you know
start piling the message traffic in
front of them
then there's no incentive to report
anything from the press or anything
that's unclassified
unless you're using classified material
then your work as an analyst is
considered inferior so that's one of the
reasons why I I sort of feel liberated
these days because I go on the internet
and get access to really better
information than what I was getting on
the inside when I had I had access to
classified information up until about
three years ago so it's just the
combination of that if you would call it
the lack of expertise the incentives to
promote people
um I I give I give you my own personal
experience what happened to me I had a
new branch chief a woman named Mary
McCarthy she admit she came out of
Africa and John knows her very well so
um unbeknownst to me uh we were asked to
provide the front office and this was in
the days we just got computers but we're
still using hard copy pieces of paper
so we're asked to provide the front
office the top 10 15 cables you know
human reports State Department reports
DOD anything that they should pay
attention to
so I'd go through and call it and send
it up to the to the front office and I
did that that went on for two months
came time to get promoted I get called
into the deputy uh director's office in
that Branch Carmen Medina you remember
Karma Carmen so I think I'm still
Facebook friends with her oh my god I
think I'm not so she she sits me down
and she just says well you didn't get
promoted because and listen to this we
had questions about the Integrity of
your analysis
and my my eyes did one of those you know
Roger Rabbit things where the eyeballs
poke out and the steam comes out of the
ears and I was like what are you talking
about
well it turned out that unbeknownst to
me Mary McCarthy who didn't speak
Spanish who had never served in Central
America who had no background in it
whatsoever she was picking out her own
group of cables every day sending it
forward to the front office
and for two months the front office was
getting one stack for me which was
radically different from what she was
doing because what she was sending up
was horseshit she had she was sending
the propaganda and the crap that was
coming from the field hmm my point is
the first day that happened
any competent manager should have called
us both in and said what the hell's
going on Mary why are you sending this
and Larry why doesn't yours match
no they let it go on for two months
and then we had questions about your
integrity and so that's why we didn't
report uh promote you that was when I
knew I had to get the [__] out of that
place yeah there was let me ask you
something when they say that we question
your integrity are they saying that
you're a traitor or no they're saying I
lied
I was lying and shading the intelligence
Jesus
yeah so that and this was that was Karma
Medina and Kate Hall
so yeah I'll call him out that that that
I mean this is really fascinating why
would anybody assume that you're lying I
mean you you are an American uh uh Larry
Johnson sorry that doesn't sound like
Honduran to me okay so the notion that
you're lying what what reason would you
have to lie why well it's just well a
political reason that I that I wanted to
I wanted to make things look better for
the Contours or I wanted to make things
look worse for the contrast the reality
was my analysis was pointing out that
there was not a lot of support in
Honduras in particular for maintaining
the Contra presence there at the time
and therefore what I was pushing from an
analytical line was going against what
the directorate of operations was
supporting so it was creating a
political Conflict for the branch
because then it was they were getting
messages back from the White House and
other places about why aren't why aren't
you people being team players
so this notion of being a team player is
you support the policy so but the fact
that they had questions about that for
me was on the very first day or the
second day they had questions they
should have called us both in confronted
us with it and said what's going on at
which point I would have been able to
explain that she didn't know that my
branch chief Mary didn't know what she
was talking about because she did not
have the experience just because she'd
been at CIA longer than me didn't mean
that she had actual substantive
knowledge about the area and
particularly about the Intel well what's
fascinating about this that you're that
you're describing Larry is that of
course this happened in Honduras in the
80s right we got to expand it to the
entire world in so far as the CIA is
concerned because the world is the
purview of the global American Empire
and you know realize that in all of
these this analysis some sort of similar
kind of incompetence is going on and
therefore the intelligence that is being
reported by the CIA to decision makers
is completely number one wrong and then
it starts to become
the policy drives the intelligence
that's provided as opposed to the
intelligence providing a true picture of
the reality on the ground would that be
correct John
yeah I think I think you've hit it on
the head and I think everything that
Larry said is is also right on this is
an ongoing theme in in the uh in the CIA
it's not it's not just in operations as
Larry says it's also prevalent in
analysis too you know the part of the
problem of the CIA is is everybody
thinks that he or she is the smartest
person in the room and there's nothing
that anybody can tell them that is gonna
that's gonna change their mind or that's
going to teach them something new and
like Larry correctly said if somebody
has been there longer and they went to
you know some great School
uh they just automatically think that
they're smarter than you are even though
you're the substantive expert on these
kinds of things you happen to be younger
and more Junior in the hierarchy but
they just think that they're smarter
than you and if they don't like your
analysis they're going to go around you
whether it's to the office director or
to the president of the United States or
to somebody in between that happens
every single day at the CIA and I'll add
too that you know we criticize uh the
cia's operational elements a lot right
they've they've fallen on their face a
million times uh we know what happened
uh up until 1975 thanks to the church
committee but what we often don't focus
on is the cia's analytic failures if
somebody were to go back and take a look
at all of the major world events from
the creation of the CIA with the
National Security Act of 1947 onward I
think we would learn that the CIA
missed every major world event
analytically they either missed it
completely or they got it wrong whether
it was you know the the Berlin airlift
the events surrounding the Berlin
airlift or the Suez Crisis in 56 or the
The Six Day War or whatever the the fall
of the Berlin Wall uh the Iranian
hostage crisis you name the major world
event and I guarantee to you that the
CIA got it wrong yeah is it is it almost
like you know that whenever the CIA says
left you have to turn right I think so
what do you think Larry so one of the
things has happened
um it's it's been an evolution when the
CIA was first set up you did have a
separation strong separation between the
operation side of dialysis and the
analytical side of the house
and uh part of that was the unders you
know that I think the the Ops people
understood that they would be in a
position to manipulate uh the analytical
side and they literally had doors that
in the in the first CIA headquarters
constructed out in McLean Virginia they
had doors in the middle of the building
that would separate people from
operations and Analysis so you were you
were literally physically kept apart
then somewhere I think it was late 70s
early 80s they opened the doors so now
there was interaction and exchange uh
what I experienced uh as the you know I
I did a stint on the opposite in the
Central American task force so I had
connections and ties with people there
but then I became the Honduran analyst
and the Honduras as functioning at the
time as the aircraft carrier for the
contrast you know a land-based aircraft
carrier
and
um the pressure that was coming the the
Ops people when they get involved with
covert action and when I'm referring to
covert action let's say our main
training equipping the contras helping
them carry out
um military attacks in Nicaragua and
other places
those officers who are invested in that
their their success depends upon the
success of what's happening on the
ground
so therefore they're going to do
everything in their power to make sure
that that looks as good as possible even
up to an including lying and I had the
experience once where we were reading
about the the upside was issuing uh the
T it's called TD it's a human report and
the human report was a was detailing and
attack but the contrast had allegedly
take carried out
but we had no other corresponding
evidence of it no overhead imagery no
intercepts what happened was uh the guy
who was running the program first name
by John he was a he was a frustrated
West Point he graduated from West Point
67. and what he was doing was he was
actually writing out himself the
operations orders for the contrast
sending it down to them and then at the
point of date and time he would issue it
as if it had actually happened even
though it hadn't happened okay so
This lends itself to all kinds of
corruption where this genre you think
okay I'm sorry you know I I'm not
intelligence man I'm Mr director dummy
so so basically yeah was he skimming off
the top in particular in this issue
you know it had it when you come up for
your annual report you got to be able to
show your Fitness report the the par as
it's called you got to be able to have
some you know you do you get decide all
these accomplishments that you carried
out even though they may not have
actually happened now that was 30 years
ago okay uh actually almost 40 years ago
so what has happened what's happened
since then it's gotten worse because now
they've created these centers where the
analysts and The Operators are share the
same space so right now I would like you
to imagine that you are a Russian
analyst and you're sitting in this task
force that's been set up to monitor what
the events in Ukraine
how do you think it's going to go over
if you come in and say the reality is
the Russians felt compelled to launch
this military operation because of what
the United States and NATO was doing
with respect to expanding NATO to
Ukraine do you think you'd be allowed to
say that no would you be allowed to
write that no because it goes against
the the this policy decision to send
complete military and intelligence
support to Ukraine regardless of what
the facts are on the ground
yeah when when Larry and I were we're
analysts
um there was a Chinese wall between
analysis and operations uh there was a
period where
um you know we had to be buzzed in to
the operational uh offices right we we
didn't have the ability to just walk
around freely around the building
um
I think it was actually better back in
those days because as Larry says uh
correctly we've got these centers now
where everybody's sitting together the
operations people the in the analysis
people the Science and Tech people there
are a couple of FBI agents there's an
NSA rep there's some guy from you know
Customs and Border Protection or
whatever everybody's sitting together in
these in these centers and then group
thinks sets in so if you're an analyst
and your job is to prevent to present
rather a completely independent view
based on your reading of the
intelligence but then the people you're
sitting around are saying no no no no
you're getting it wrong
um even if you're not uh we need to
protect these and these uh operational
equities or you can't say that because
they're they're going to be pissed off
at the White House at the NSC so you
have to change it to this well then
you've got this completely mucked up
analysis that's wrong and is not what
you intended in the first place and
you're only you're only presenting it
because it's going to keep everybody in
your silly Center uh Happy well that's
not that's not service to the country
that's not public service
that's just going along to get along and
that's what leads to intelligence
failure after intelligence failure yeah
because to talk about the specific
situation in Ukraine you know I mean uh
what Larry was saying that yeah no
analyst is going to tell the truth and
and so how are how is the public at
large and decision makers in particular
going to make the right decisions
because what's what's obvious to
everybody who's in the alt commentarian
Community if you will the YouTube you
know the this little um circle of people
who are watching this like like it's a
Mexican soap opera right uh you know we
are getting the correct information
because we are predicting things that
are going to happen correctly whereas in
the west they they are just out to lunch
I mean like I remember uh before when
the conflict first started I was talking
to a friend of mine uh in the financial
community and and he's a pretty Sharp
customer and very well informed and he
said these sanctions aren't going to do
anything to Russia they will probably
hurt the West
and and of course the decision makers
went Full Throttle on the sanctions and
exactly what the guy said the guy works
at Investment Bank and his job was to
now analyze this stuff but his job was
to present realistic analysis whereas
the CIA the the publicly funded
intelligence agencies seemed to be
completely off base you know I mean
wouldn't it be better to just shut down
the CIA and and just follow the Duran
and a few other channels well I think
Larry and I have both have both
advocated that yeah yes you know can I
had something to I I did an analysis one
time I was a junior analyst and I did an
analysis on um on a popular Uprising in
Bahrain and I said I believed that the
Bahraini royal family would muddle
through they would give the opposition
just enough to calm them down without
giving them any real freedom and they
would muddle through that that ended up
being what happened but I was I was
taking a task over that analysis and I
was told that I needed to start thinking
outside the box I freaking hate that
phrase first of all Yes I need to think
out of box out of the box and I said to
my boss I said listen you gotta make
stuff up that's what it means well you
took the words out of my mouth I said to
my boss
there's a difference between doing
thoughtful analysis and just making [__]
up and you want me to just make [__] up
yeah and I can't do that
but uh that happens every single day
yeah yeah guys by the way I just want to
mention the fact that we've crossed the
3 500 Mark in so far as concurrent
viewers and I'm urging all of my viewers
who are interested in Larry and John to
check out their links they're in the
description below and as a pinned
comment I just want to like you know
throw that out there so that everybody
knows where they can find them but
anyway John I'm sorry I cut you off no
no you didn't go ahead you're okay
you're cutting me off I'm upset Noah oh
so yeah you know it must be my Larry
phobia because everything is a phobia
nowadays there's trans
that phobia it's Larry phobia well you
know there are
a couple of other changes that have
taken place so let's call it sort of
institutionally or procedurally
so the the phenomena that John and I are
describing of political influence over
the intelligence analysis process is not
new uh I I was fortunate that I was
taught in the new analyst course by an
old analyst by the name of George Allen
wow Allen was the division Chief over
the Vietnam War and he was the one who
had an analyst by the name of Sam Adams
literally a descendant of Sam Adams and
the the advantage that Sam Adams had as
an analyst was he had lived in Vietnam
he knew the terrain but he was also
wealthy he was a multi-millionaire so he
had what is called [__] you money so
they're because they couldn't threaten
if they threatened him with loss of his
job no big deal he was going to survive
and be able to feed his family
and what George Allen described to to us
my class there were about 12 of us in
there he described what it was like he
was getting phone calls from Lyndon
Baines Johnson from Robert McNamara the
Secretary of Defense he was getting from
the National Security advisor and the
the it was over and over this pressure
why don't you be a team player you know
why aren't you why are you saying that
the the Viet Cong have all of this uh
extra forces when we've killed them all
and you know that was sort of the basic
issue and he and he told us he said I
regret that I didn't push back harder he
said because at the time I had two kids
one was in high school one was starting
College I didn't have any money to fall
back on so he was basically a hostage to
his economic situation unable to tell
the truth about what was going on
but the other change that's taking place
is back in that era in the 60s and 70s
the CIA still had a very good human
ability where our case officers go
overseas and persuade foreigners to come
to Quran to spy for us and to give us
information and between their own
countries what has happened started in
the late 90s accelerated into the 2000s
over Reliance on liaison reporting where
our intelligence comes from a foreign
intelligence service and it just gets
passed to us and then we put it out
which is why what's going on with a lot
of the so-called analysis right now with
respect to Ukraine it's coming from the
ukrainians whatever the ukrainians tell
us these analysts are repeating and
they're not they're not even going out
to challenge it critically
so that's uh you know that is absolutely
correct absolutely correct you know I I
worked for a a CIA deputy director it
was my last headquarters job I was his
executive assistant and he used to say
all the time that the job of the CIA is
actually quite simple it's to recruit
spies to steal secrets and then to
analyze those secrets to allow our
policy makers to make the best informed
policy and on paper that's perfect
that's exactly what the CIA should be
doing but in reality the CIA has never
done that never they've done things like
you know uh smuggle uh Nazi war
criminals into the country or to
infiltrate U.S media organizations uh or
to uh to to drug people as we said at
the start of the show just to see how
they react or uh you know rather than
developing so sources and let me tell
you it's hard work I spend eight years
in operations it's hard to convince
somebody to commit Espionage for you
yeah or to commit treason for you just
because you're a nice guy and they enjoy
your company and you're gonna pay them a
lot of money in the end but it's hard
work well it's not hard work to drive to
the Ukrainian intelligence service every
morning and say what do you got for me
today and then you go back to the
station and you type it into the cia's
computer system and say Here's a liaison
report which then the White House or the
Pentagon or the CIA promptly leaks to
the New York Times or the Washington
Post to make it look like the ukrainians
are going to win this war
yeah I mean because they're they're not
winning it's it's catastrophic quite
frankly right I want to ask you
something uh to flip the coin if you
will do you think that similar problems
are befalling the Russians or the
Chinese for that matter or do you think
that they have organized their
intelligence services in a in a more
rational sense to order in order to get
a better sense of reality
I think the Chinese because of the the
money that they have
um you know they don't spend their money
like we do on on ridiculously expensive
uh defense projects they they have a lot
of
um free cash flow and so they've coupled
the collection of human intelligence
with electronic collection of
intelligence
um the Russians do it the old-fashioned
way they recruit human sources to to
give them information
um it's something that we've gotten away
from in a in a really bad way now with
that said
and I'll I'll repeat myself uh I'm on
record as saying that I don't think we
should have a CIA not that a CIA
wouldn't be valuable if it could be
trusted and and successfully and
efficiently overseen by by uh the House
and Senate intelligence committees but
it's proven over the course of 75 years
that it can't be trusted to do that
and so you know we've got the state
Department's Bureau of intelligence and
research for example that does fantastic
analysis we have a a division of not a
division but a a bureau of the
Department of Defense called defense
Human Services that does exactly what
CIA operations does it develops human
sources we've got NSA that does
electronic uh intelligence collection
we've got DARPA that does all the
experimentation and the scientific uh
and technological advancements there's
there's no reason to have this out of
control uh body called the CIA it's it's
doing the American people a disservice
yeah no but I I when I refer to the
Russian intelligence services and the
Chinese intelligence Services why I'm
interested in knowing is are they
providing their leadership their
respective leaderships with accurate
information uh with an accurate analysis
of the of the of the ground situation
because it's seems to me that what's
going on with the CIA and Western
intelligence Services generally is that
they are providing the leadership cost
with a completely distorted view of
reality and so they keep constantly
being caught flat-footed they they
they're like how did this happen we were
winning like for instance in this
situation here there is inevitably going
to be a moment of collapse of the
zelinski regime it's it's on the horizon
and everybody in Washington is going to
be like what happened you know like well
they did they did the same with that I
mean the same thing happened with
Afghanistan For Heaven's Sake okay just
two years ago so what what you're seeing
is we we've witnessed a complete role
reversal
what the Soviet Union used to be the
United States is
what the United States used to be Russia
is becoming yeah and what I mean by that
is in the Soviet era there the the Party
politics and the the the people who need
to sort of tell people up on top what
they wanted to hear was very very strong
and that when you have a very
centralized system that it inevitably it
caters or panders to the person at the
top uh and by contrast the more
decentralized it is the more likely you
are to actually get some real
information and I'm sorry I think the
Russians I think the Russians are far
superior to the United States on that
account and I don't I don't think
there's there really is at this point no
incentive to lie to Vladimir Putin or
talaveroff or to the the rest of the or
to garasimov and the military leadership
there because they recognize the
survival as a nation is not stick this
we're talking extensions
yeah focuses it you can't [__] when
there's a real chance that you're gonna
be overrun so so they have to be and and
so you think that maybe the CIA the the
problem of it is that it it consider it
has always considered the United States
so rich and Powerful that it sort of
like almost doesn't matter because you
know I mean things will work themselves
out so it's okay if we cut Corners that
kind of mentality
yeah well
we're terrible at self-reflection
because if we would simply be honest
with ourselves
step back and look at the record of the
last 60 years
from Vietnam to the the futile Wars in
Central America to two Wars in Iraq to a
war in Afghanistan this this pox
American
instead of pax America it's been more
like pox Americana okay and it's it's an
infection upon the world I'm gonna I'm
gonna steal that that's a good one yeah
feel free that was our model at CIA
anything worth doing well as we're
stealing from someone else okay
the only the only place you'd ever work
where plagiarism was encouraged and
rewarded you know so that was so true
oh true they they look merving yeah
plagiarism
so it goes in different directions and
you just claim credit for it
yeah so because the thing that drives me
up the wall is that see from the sea
because it seems at this time that we
have the following situation in the west
where we have these intelligent services
that get this information and they have
a bunch of press people that are more or
less I don't think that they're on their
payroll per se but they provide
exclusive information so these various
journalists can show up to their
editor's offices and say hey here I got
something from this CIA guy you know
it's real intelligent stuff and so the
the CIA is providing uh false
information because of the reasons that
we discussed previously and providing
that information to the press that
regurgitates it and spreads it out and
propagandizes the people into believing
things that are simply not true uh yeah
Alexander mercuris in in yesterday's
show and I always recommend Alexander
and the Durant they're fantastic he
mentioned the fact that the Wall Street
Journal I haven't read this article I'm
just going by his account but he's is
always you know on point and reliable he
says how the Washington uh they excuse
me the Wall Street Journal put out an
article talking about Putin and
basically characterizing him as you know
uh uh um you know Hitler in in the in
the days as as Berlin was falling you
know and and issuing nonsensical orders
and pacing around and being hysterical
which could not be further from the
truth I mean because everybody's been
noticing the various meetings that Putin
has been running they're very competent
and very on point and I mean he seems to
be like a man in charge in full and
everybody seems to be lockstepped not
fearful of him but rather yeah we agree
let's go where this guy is telling us to
go or leading us towards and so the Wall
Street Journal which is supposed to be a
reputable news
um uh news site a newspaper
is spewing things that are objectively
not true and the smarter people who read
the new The Wall Street Journal are
saying to themselves well this must be
true and it's just [__] and I'm like
dude what the hell is going on with you
so my point is do you do you think that
the way the system has become organized
I'm not saying that there's some cabal
or something I think it's a Natural
Evolution but do you think that the way
the system is currently organizing
whereby information coming erroneous
information erroneous analysis coming
from intelligence Services is being
passed to reporters and essentially
being propagandized well but is it
erroneous in the option I I maybe you're
giving them too much credit you know
there was a there was a thing in the in
the Press just a few weeks ago about uh
russiagate where a Washington Post
editor had emailed
um a reporter the reporter had gotten
some information from the CIA saying uh
the Russian were involved in getting
Trump elected and he was saying this
just sounds wrong to me and and the
editor wrote back and said
um
but if anybody would know wouldn't they
know I can't believe they would get
something like this wrong well it's not
an issue of getting it wrong it's that
they're lying to you yeah you know
there's a fantastic journalist who's now
at Bloomberg
um uh he used to be with uh oh my gosh
we started off with the LA times but
anyway Jason Leopold Jason Leopold has
been described by a senior DOD official
as a foia terrorist because he has made
more Freedom of Information Act requests
than any other person in the world right
really he's the one who used foia for
example to break the Hillary Clinton
email story so what he did this is about
I don't know two or three years ago he
sent a foia request to the CIA asking
for copies of all Communications between
the cia's office of public affairs and
journalists all journalists and what he
found among other things was as a series
of emails traded between CIA and
kendallanian who is the lead National
Security correspondent for NBC News and
MSNBC and he found that kendallanian was
sending his articles to the CIA for
clearance before he was sending them to
his own editor
and what do you another thing that he
found was that
was that the cia's office of public
affairs was warning journalists
not to publish anti-cia information or
they would not be invited to the
Christmas party anymore oh my God yeah
let me slit my wrist oh my God yeah and
we you know we talk about operation
Mockingbird for example where until 1975
the CIA was recruiting journalists or or
placing CIA officers in journalistic
Outlets they don't need to do that
anymore
the journalists now do it for free
because first of all most Outlets don't
have a budget for investigative
journalism right and secondly you know
the CIA is going to give you a scoop you
just it you put your name in the byline
you make it onto the front page you get
promoted that's just what they do now
that's just a reality of today's media
so just a series of bad uh uh uh
motivations about incentives Miss
incentives is creating this this uh the
situation where lies from the
intelligence Community are passed on to
journalists whose few more lies and it
just expands the lies all over the place
until the people have a completely
distorted sense of reality
the real flaw is as long as covert
action is allowed to remain part of the
CIA it will never be able to reform
itself
I I agree with John that it probably
ought to just be burned to the ground uh
I would start it over I think I think
there is a need for if you will a
professional Cadre of analysts but in
but genuinely independent analysts and
and the problem with with a creature
like the CIA is it's sort of like that
dog you have at home that wants to go
out for a walk so the CIA eagerly waits
for the treats that the White House will
throw it or for the pat on the head for
boy that was great analysis and up until
the point that you're actually pointing
out that uh that hey you know you guys
at the White House you've [__] the bed
well they don't want to hear that you
know they don't want to be told that
they need to go buy some depends and put
those on
um so you've always got this this
tension where as long as covert action
is operating it does it's going to
actually drive the attempts to recruit
human sources if that's going on and so
you're going to always have corrupted
intelligence produced by the directorate
of operations if you're going to have a
covert action capability it needs to be
walled off be its own agency but then
that's something that frankly is really
dangerous because when you look at our
history as John mentioned earlier the
history of covert action is not a one
with uh great success scattered about
it's nothing familiar after failure or
where we make the world worse off not
better off yeah yeah exactly right you
know because I I think to myself you
know of of uh different kinds of
analyzes that I I uh that I've come
across uh mostly Financial quite frankly
and that Financial that financial
analysis is usually spot on if if some
financial analyst is saying oh it's more
or less like this you you can take it to
the bank because money is riding on
these decisions there are consequences
immediately if an analysis uh an analyst
says you know buy this Bond or don't buy
this Bond you know a lot of money can be
lost or won depending on the correct uh
uh analysis right but insofar as a CIA
and these intelligence services are
concerned there's no consequences it
seems to me I mean that that you know uh
Vladimir Putin tomorrow is going to be
replaced by a purple kangaroo as the
president of the Russian Federation I
say this as an analyst at the CIA and
you know it proves out to be wrong of
course and nothing happens to me no but
that's but that's the reality and that's
the reality in the CIA for years I
worked for a guy who um who had been a
Saudi analyst and then moved into
management and when he made it up to
gs14 he told a group of us that he was
going to make a name for himself
by saying over and over and over again
to everybody who would listen that the
Saudi royal family would be overthrown
and so this became his thing it became a
joke for us but as administrations
change and you know new people coming
into these positions just don't know any
better this is a really powerful
briefing that they get when they first
win the presidential election that the
Saudi royal family is going to be
overthrown well he made it up into the
senior intelligence service level one
level two level three level four he ends
up one of the one of the Deputy
directors of the CIA
even though the Saudi royal family Not
only was never overthrown but is
probably in a stronger position now than
it ever has been in its history yeah the
truth never mattered What mattered was
he came across as a smart guy who had
lived in the region and spoke Arabic and
he really passionately believed this
could be true in fact he didn't
passionately believe it to be true he
believed that it would set him apart
from everybody else saying that there
was no danger to the Saudi royal family
and he was the one that got promoted
yeah in fact if you screw up you're most
likely to get promoted you get rewarded
not punished I mean I have uh one of my
uh so in the first year I was there I
was in the career trainee program and
this this is one of the first runnings
where in the past the career trainee
program was only for future case
officers people who were going to go out
and try to recruit spies but I was in
the era when they had both analysts and
operations people and Science and
Technology and admin people so Valerie
plain for example was part of my class
uh so one of my classmates uh his first
assignment was in Costa Rica and what he
discovered was that his the predecessor
that had been there before him had
recruited supposedly recruited some
agents that were giving information on
the sandinistas
it turned out the guy had fabricated him
so so my my friend he disclosed the
fabrication pointed it out he got a
twenty thousand dollar bonus doing it
the guy that had created the false
agents he later wound up as chief of
station in Romania
oh so I I mean but that's the point that
lack accountability because that's what
we're really talking about here if
people are going to be held accountable
for the decisions they make if they get
people killed or if they get if they if
they cause Major Mayhem or give the
wrong coordinates and you bomb the
Chinese Embassy in Sudan you know we go
down the list and that was the one thing
that I I really saw lacking out there
and I don't know what John's experience
was but the utter lack of accountability
that's something else that we're seeing
across the board in Western Society a
lack of accountability you are
completely incompetent and what happens
to you you get kicked upstairs look at
Kamala Harris look at Ursula Wonderland
she was a current EU commissioner
president she was the Minister of
Defense of Germany and she was under
disaster and she got kicked upstairs
it's almost like you know if you're
competent your career is cratered but if
you're an idiot you get a better
position with a better salary how did
this happen uh in in the in your view
that that that failure is rewarded that
incompetence gets you ahead how did this
happen I mean this is a genuine question
and I'm asking you in so far as your
expertise in the CIA concerned but I'm
interested in it as a general problem
that I view in the West
John
well
I mean it's a tough problem it's a tough
question yeah it's a tough question uh
and I think that there are several
answers one it's very much an old boys
club and now an old boys and girls club
where at the top at that senior level
level they're all friends and they all
um take care of one another now there's
some notable exceptions of course where
personalities conflict and and they go
after each other but for the most part
they all look out for each other at that
very senior level
um another thing that that I sort of
came into contact with when dealing with
people at that level
is that they're also afraid that if
somebody in a senior position becomes
disgruntled that they'll go to the media
and that would be disastrously
embarrassing you know I worked for a
woman
um who
had never uh I worked for her in
operations she had never been a case
officer she was what was called a
reports officer meaning when the case
officer collected the raw intelligence
she would make sure that the formatting
was correct and the source descriptor
was correct and she would send it into
headquarters for release
well in the 1980s
a large group of of female CIA
operations employees filed a class
action suit saying that they had been
discriminated against because they were
women they had been discriminated
against and so in the eastern district
of Virginia a judge found that they had
indeed been discriminated against he
said he said in his decision that he had
never seen a defendant in a case
um so deeply document its own crime as
the CIA did by like they they turned
over in Discovery memos saying oh don't
promote her she's a woman promote the
guy instead like they actually wrote
this down and kept it so they're
supposed to be intelligence man yeah so
every every woman in operations got a
two grade promotion so you go from a 12
to a 14 that's a significant that's a
significant promotion a 13 to a 15.
these are very significant promotions
well she was one of those people that
got the to grade promotion she had never
been on a covert to a covert meeting in
her life she had never recruited a spy
in her life but all of a sudden she
became the chief of the biggest station
in the world
and then on the strength of that
became the deputy director of National
Intelligence
that kind of thing happens a lot where
this woman this woman Excuse excuse the
pun she was a boob I mean I I never I
never worked for anybody who was so cut
off from the day-to-day life of an
operations officer and frankly had no
idea what the analysts did all day long
she had no idea nor did she care
um who made it literally to the very top
of the intelligence community
Jesus right well what about our current
director of CIA is Burns oh yeah Burns
is uh he's sort of the worst from the
standpoint with his Heritage as a
Foreign Service Officer yeah you know he
underst he understands the business of
intelligence but he's just he's a
political Adam
and that's that's the problem with this
you've got to try to divorce the
politics if you're going to get a real
intelligence done
the politics have got to be divorced
from it I'd go and suggesting that I'm
incredibly naive but it is really you
need somebody that's going to tell you
the truth you know hey honey do I look
fat in this dress well you know
you're you know if you're married you
know that the correct answer to that is
no so or if you want to say me you look
lovely yeah that's that's an example
where politics comes into interferes
with doing real intelligence analysis as
opposed to said yeah you know you could
drop a few pounds and you'd look better
you know that would be the truth but you
get in trouble unfortunately I I think
what has allowed this political
corruption to take place has been been
because we've not faced an existential
threat in the United States
sense
since we since the Civil War yeah yeah I
mean World War One World War II Korea
none of those posed existential threats
to us so as a result you could always
get away with hiring Fredo to do the
bookkeeping okay and that's right yeah I
mean it's just uh it is it's the kind of
thing that where you're it's not life
and death because when it gets down to
life and death if you look back at the
founding of the the Republic here in the
in the United States that uh those men
who gathered in Philadelphia and put
this documents together
um they were had flaws and they were far
from perfect and they allowed you know
slavery but uh there was a level of
competence among them that was
extraordinary that when you compare that
with the current group of folks that
inhabit Congress and the you know the
halls of the senator or the House of
Representatives it was a calling
I was just reading the other day as an
example the the Republicans elected a
guy up in New York who lied I mean
Santos unbelievable he lied about
everything that he had he was excited
about being gay he said that he's been
openly gay for 10 years and he was
married to a woman until a year and a
half ago
okay that's a first that's a first you
know so lying about being in the closet
yeah yeah so I
I wonder if YouTube would would bump me
in the algorithm if I had claimed I was
gay or maybe said I identify as a woman
would that help I don't know
that's the way to go nowadays
Jesus hey by the way um I'm gonna uh
we've got like 4 200 concurrent viewers
Chad thank you so much I I appreciate it
why don't you give our guests a plus one
if you are appreciating this
conversation because it's a delight as
far as I'm concerned and um yeah I'm
gonna bring on uh one of my longtime
supporters on patreon uh to ask a
question and to patreon supporters we're
going to do a couple of questions but
please be to the point and brief please
thank you uh JJ how's it going man it's
going very well thank you
um I'm rather late so this may have
already been covered
um but uh can you talk about the stove
piping of intelligence services
um for the Iraq War and
um what happened with David Kelly
wow who's that who's David who's David
Kelly
Dr David Kelly who apparently well The
Story Goes that he committed suicide he
was a weapons inspector that came out
and said that the dossier was fake was
all sexed up I believe was the term at
the time and uh basically
um he came out said this then he
suddenly turns up dead
um the working theory is that it was a
foreign intelligence service which I'm
not going to name because I don't want
to be accused of being anti-semitic but
you can guess from that which one it was
I I'm surprised you haven't heard of him
yeah yeah but but he was not the only
one he wasn't the only one saying that
the the the claims about weapons of mass
destruction were false I mean you had
Scott Ritter was very prominent at the
time and in fact ended up uh resigning
oh I think over that very issue just
that they were being ignored so uh it
was uh and then you know what was going
on at CIA uh my my former colleague
Valerie plain I mean Valor I know was
honestly looking because they had all
these reports coming out but they could
never verify and corroborate and then
they began to see it was complete
disinformation yeah so
um I I don't I don't think Kelly was
necessarily so prominent that he needed
to be taken out because the message was
getting out there through other means as
well
John it was it was my understanding that
his his wife later said that it was a it
was a suicide with that said
um JJ is right uh that intelligence
service has a very long track record of
taking out
anybody who might perhaps maybe someday
pose a problem to them uh they they very
proudly took credit for the Gerald Bull
assassination back in what was it 1990
the spring of 1990 uh and and Untold
number of Iranian
um nuclear scientists uh it would take
us hours to talk about the the stove
piping of intelligence
um in the run-up of the Iraq War the
stove piping can you can you explain
that please yeah you know there was a
lot of intelligence out there saying
that the Iraqis just simply did not have
a program to develop weapons of mass
destruction it just didn't right and I
remember being an observer not a
participant but I was there as a note
taker for a meeting between CIA analysts
and Department of energy analysts on
what had and had not been developed on
this Iraqi program and it became a
shouting match because the department of
energy analysts kept saying there is no
evidence that the Iraqis are developing
weapons of mass destruction and I'll
tell you what convinced me that they
were right
was that Saddam Hussein's two
sons-in-law Hussein kamela majeed and
Saddam camel amaji they had been married
to saddam's uh two daughters uh uh two
of the three daughters Rana and rugged
uh they defected to Jordan and the CIA
sent a team not of operational people
but of analysts to go out to Jordan and
um and debrief them and
one of those people was a boss of mine
he told me when he got back that as soon
as they walked into the room uh Hussein
camel who had been saddam's minister of
industry and Military industrialization
he was in charge of the wmd program
he's dead that
the Iraqis
destroyed all of their weapons of mass
destruction after the first Gulf War
because they were so afraid that Scott
Ritter and his teams were going to find
something that it would allow the
Americans an opening to attack the
country again
and so
you know a biological weapons program
you can set up in in your kitchen all
you need is a sink and a stove and a
refrigerator and you've got to buy a
weapons lab so that was easy but the
nuclear uh
program was
well documented to have been uh disabled
and and uh destroyed well before a
decade before the Gulf War the CW
chemical weapons program was a little
bit harder but but Hussein Campbell said
no in in 1991 and 1992 that whole
program was done away with
the CIA just chose to either not believe
it or to ignore it and then to sort of
beat that drum for the next 10 years
until George W bush became president and
he was comfortable enough allowing Dick
Cheney and Donald Rumsfeld at all
to take falsified intelligence from
Ahmed telabi and the Iraqi National
Congress to to lay this false uh this
false premise for for war
yeah the the other the other element of
stove piping is that information that's
kept within CIA channels is not shared
with FBI as an example I mean that was
really the that was really the most
prominent case of the stove piping in
the lead up to 911 and 11. that with
information that the CIA had that was
FBI agents who were detailed out to the
agency were unable to share it back with
FBI headquarters which you know may have
made a difference and uh it was this
protection you know there are lots of
different theories and explanations for
why that was done but that failure to
use the use compartmentation of
information to prevent it from being
shared where you get to see the whole
picture well until 2003 the CIA and FBI
computer systems were incompatible with
one another right and so if something
was reported in CIA channels the the FBI
had no access to it and vice versa
finally the the CIA named a CIA officer
as deputy director of the FBI for
counterterrorism and the FBI named a
senior FBI agent as as deputy director
of the cia's counter-terrorism center so
there was that forced cooperation but
Larry's exactly right uh stove piping in
that in that example led to the deaths
of thousands of of Americans just simply
because the CIA and the FBI hated each
other yeah and then on on top of it when
when Edward Snowden did what he did
um and I personally view Snowden as a
hero myself
um what what he did up to that point I
was scripting exercises with the U.S
military Special Operations Command and
we would have full access to CI to State
Department of messages
once that happened
they went back to stove piping they cut
off all DOD Personnel were cut off from
the state department message traffic
so yeah you know it's they keep talking
if we we do it and then they go back to
the old habits of uh not sharing
information across uh you know across
the agencies agencies become very
protective and parochial of their
interests
yeah
is that my thing my thinking is let's
see like with what happened in 2003
uh insofar as you know there are no
weapons of mass destruction and so
um you know that that comes out after
the invasion has happened but it's still
during the Bush Administration and so
there are no consequences to the to the
CIA or the Intelligence on the contrary
because they they gave the justification
for what they wanted irrespect I mean
they were gonna they were gonna invade
anyway and it was just uh there's some
clicking going on I don't know who's
Mike or or somebody like
at top tapping anyway there was there
was there were some there were some
consequences Gonzalo but the
consequences were for Joe Wilson and
Valerie playing yeah that's right they
went after Joe told the truth he said
that there was a lie that was sold to
the American people and they they went
out and destroyed him and then they they
ended up destroying Valerie so if you're
in government at that point the message
is loud and clear if you dare to tell
the truth they're gonna get you
Jesus JJ does it answer your question
yeah yes that was an excellent answer
um also what about the collapse of human
intelligence and uh tradecraft and now
the over Reliance of uh Communications
uh because everything seems to have
shifted that way and there seem to be
very few assets on the ground uh I know
in the US military they've got the
activity but you know there seems to be
a complete loss of networks can you talk
about that
we actually covered that a little
earlier yeah yeah a little earlier but
the question I have specifically about
that issue is that when was the decision
made not to cultivate human intelligence
was it a specific decision or did it
sort of like Peter out on its own
no it developed over the years you know
it it probably started at the beginning
of the Clinton Administration uh the the
CIA underwent something called a cull
where
um where the white house uh told the CIA
we've got to fire every clandestine
source that we have who has a a problem
with human rights which was a noble
thing to do
but um
but it it results
can you expand on that I don't
understand yeah yeah so so let's say uh
you are uh the leader of a debt Squad in
uh yeah
in El Salvador or Nicaragua or whatever
um no Uruguay Uruguay please because
it's got better yeah right okay better
beaches so the CIA wasn't going to do
business with you anymore so we're gonna
we're gonna cut you off we can't talk to
you anymore because you're a human
rights violator that's an that's a noble
thing to do but if you want information
on what the other members of the death
squad are doing
yeah uh then you know John McCain once
said that it's difficult to be in
business with pigs
um you're gonna get dirty by Rolling in
the mud with the pig but the pig enjoys
it
so you know you've you've got to make a
decision a policy decision about whether
or not
you're gonna lay down with monsters
and well in terms of getting information
it would I mean if your job is to get
accurate information yeah you're gonna
have to you can talk to Saints but
you're gonna have to talk to some demons
too A lot of them exactly the demons are
the ones who are causing the trouble
it's not exactly right and so the notion
that oh I'm not going to talk to you
because you're a human rights abuser
abuser I I don't see the Practical uh
benefit and I see a lot of practical
detriments to uh uh self-censoring
yourself because you're not going to
know what horrible people are up to
which is the whole point isn't it
well yeah and because the people you're
they're really targeting to recruit were
anybody that had any connection to the
Russians or to the Chinese uh that were
working in diplomatic jobs you know you
know really did CIA had a different
completely different cast of uh assets
compared to what DEA would get uh DEA
would actually you know you get some
people that really knew what was going
on but they were you know usually that
killed two or three people and they were
drug traffickers uh I think there was
one other Factor though that contributed
to the movement away from Human uh it
was in the night early 1990s under
Clinton that they started sending senior
analysts overseas as Chiefs of station
yes in other words you you would send
somebody like the boss in my middle
middle America Caribbean division was a
guy named Marty Rover well Rober was a
he was a character he was a porn addict
among other things you know they didn't
didn't hide it at work I mean this is
what was said oh God yeah no I mean
there were I heard some conversations
coming out of him it was just like you
know I'm thinking you're doing this at
work but he was saying he's doing that
at work imagine what he was doing at
home oh God so and then he winds up as
the chief of station I believe it was
Buenos Aires he had never taken the
field officer's training course he had
never served in a clandestine position
overseas really knew nothing about
recruiting intelligence assets and then
running them in a way to protect their
identity sounds like John Brennan yeah
yeah well exactly exactly the same thing
with Brennan sure yeah he he had he had
never spent a single day in the
directorate of operations and he becomes
the chief of station in Riyadh yeah yeah
in reality out of all places yeah
one of my one of my classmates was the
chief of base out of dehran when that
was blown up and one of the one of the
Back stories to that is they were
prevented from collecting on any
intelligence that would be terrorist
related because they didn't want to
offend the Saudis yes right so he was
prevented from being able to collect
information that probably could have uh
prevented that incident
and that was Brennan signed off Brennan
signed off on that
and JJ uh thanks for being on I'm going
to bring somebody else up thank you so
much okay by the way just finally I'd
like to say a great thank you to John
kiriako I know he's been through an
enormous amount and there's a lot of us
out here that actually really appreciate
what he's doing oh thank you so much
thank you very much that means a lot to
me I appreciate it thank you JJ I
appreciate it yeah uh let me bring in
um uh real quick let me bring in the spy
guy and spy guy is is called the spy guy
he runs a channel called the spy guy
check him out hey how's it going spygon
great this is great like uh two people I
would love to do an interview with kind
of thing uh uh you guys have shown to me
I always thought the CIA was the
sandbaggers but you're you make the
abware look good from what you're
calling me oh my God
so what's on your mind man thank you
yeah just uh
I don't know
do you have any favorites in uh in
intelligent shows or what do you think
is really a realistic show that's a good
question right that's a good question
all the questions I wanted to ask I had
to come up with something out there so I
went with that one yeah that's a great
question
um I think the best the best
um intelligence related show
um ever is the Americans okay absolutely
the best yeah and Joe Joe Weisberg the
the creator of the Americans I I worked
with him in the counter terrorism Center
fantastic guy absolutely brilliant
complete and total failure as the case
officer it just wasn't for him he just
he just didn't have it in him to ask
people to commit Espionage and so he
told me one one day that he was
resigning and I said what really I said
oh man I'm gonna be sorry to see you go
what are you gonna do and he said
um well I'm not married I don't have any
kids I'm gonna go to Hollywood and find
my fortune and he wrote a he wrote a
novel that was well received but didn't
do very well commercially it was heavily
redacted which I liked because
it showed that he was serious about it
and then he created the Americans and as
successful as the Americans
became
the CIA still insisted on reviewing and
in many cases redacting the script to
that show because they were just they
were just too true to life yeah so they
were involved in that now in terms of
movies there was a movie that came out
20 years ago called the recruit with
like
Orlando Bloom or somebody
um Pacino was in it wasn't he yeah
patino was in it exactly the first half
of that movie was 100 right on and then
the second half kind of went a little
crazy it was exactly on except they
didn't beat us in um in training I mean
training was hard it was very hard but
they didn't beat us now with that said
I'm gonna blow my own horn here
I'm the script consultant for a new show
that's going to start in March on CBS
called True Lies it's based on the James
Cameron movie of the same uh name this
show is going to be awesome it starts at
the end of March it's got a cast of
Young nobodies and there's some of the
most brilliant script writers I've ever
met
nice
I was like listening to your question
I'm like I don't know but now you know I
want to see the show
I I would weigh in with one of the
problems with the agency and and
Hollywood television movies is people
their image becomes Sean Connery yeah
Pierce Brosnan right and the reality is
I think captured by Scott Adams and his
cartoon Dilbert Dilbert is more the more
appropriate image for the CIA
indeed I'll add one other thing too too
and I don't mean to I don't mean to take
a piss on the on the parade here but um
over the last uh 10 years or so the CIA
has opened up a branch within the office
of public affairs
whose employees jobs it is to solely
liaise with Hollywood Studios so
oftentimes most of the time you're gonna
get only Pro CIA programming coming out
of LA
sure yeah which is you know not a good
thing that's not the case with True Lies
but most most CIA related Productions
are just like the FBI related
Productions were in the 50s 60s and 70s
where everything had to get the personal
approval of Jay Edgar
fair enough the spy guy I hope that
answered your question man yeah I I will
say if you guys have not seen it I would
recommend watching the sandbaggers you
can find them on YouTube it is a great
show from about British intelligence in
the 70s written by Nick uh spy himself
and uh it goes it gets really into
bureaucratic drama so I I do that with
you I I will say that my the show I like
to watch and can watch over and over is
the Lecrae Tinker Taylor Soldier Spy
the British the British version of it
not the not the American yeah the
alakiness one you can also find those on
YouTube yeah okay thanks so much spy guy
take it easy bye yep bye
uh by the way in so far as Finance is
concerned the best movie to watch about
uh an investment Bank from the inside is
Margin Call and it was uh a few years
ago yeah that was absolutely the best uh
Financial movie that gives you a sense
of real sense of what an investment bank
is like
I bring on Susie Q who's a long time
supporter and thank you so much Susie Q
for being on
Hi how are you
well um I I I have what I have a couple
of questions but this one I'm not sure
you may or may not want to answer what
happened to Gina haspel
oh I know what happened to Gina haspel
in fact
from where I'm sitting I can see the
office building where Gina haspel Works
she is now an uncredited investment
advisor at a hedge fund that's located
at the corner of 17th Street and
Pennsylvania Avenue she is not on the
funds website
she's made she's I forgot I I forgot she
was head of CIA and she there was some
uh yeah there was some
concerned that she was involved in some
activities that happened over in Germany
at the time of uh the election
well she was she was actually prior to
that she was the chief of Station in
London so she was liaison for the whole
Russia gate the involvement of British
intelligence with CIA and FBI so she was
actively involved in the plot against
Trump
yeah yeah
she was also one of the god the god
parents of the cia's torture program
infamously so yeah oh okay so she was
not on the side of the angels as it were
oh no no no no no no in fact you know
what I when she was named CIA director
The Washington Post called me and they
asked if I would write an op-ed
um about her nomination as CIA director
I said absolutely so they told me
take as many words as you want we'll put
it in on Sunday so I wrote like 1500
words and then they did a a video uh
interview to attach to the electronic uh
copy of the the uh op-ed well the day
that it ran I got a call from Rand Paul
and he said can you come to my office
and we strategize about how to block
This Woman's nomination I said
absolutely so I speed up to Capitol Hill
meet with Rand Paul and four or five of
his aides we spend a day strategizing
and then five days later he voted yes on
her nomination
really why Wow because the CIA is
wow yeah you know Chuck Schumer once
said that uh he said that if the C if
the intelligence agencies want to get
you they've got uh you know Seven Ways
to Sunday
yeah I mean nine ways from Sunday yeah
intelligence Services basically are a
black male the the lawmakers so that
they get their way is that an accurate
statement yes and it's not even
blackmail so much as it is gray mail you
know I I I went up to um
I went up to Senator Ron Wyden one time
at a dinner party I had just gotten out
of prison and I went up to him and I
said hey Senator I gotta I gotta say I
was disappointed I expected more from
you I thought you would support me more
strongly than just you know one
meaningless statement and he got very
angry and he said look it takes all of
my energy just to not lose my security
clearance
and I said oh so you're afraid of them
that's what it is wow that's my senator
I live I live in the Communist uh area
of uh Oregon so yeah that's quite
disgusting very disgusting so my next
question
um what do you think will happen now
that the Twitter files have come out and
have shown that not only were the FBI
but the CIA Homeland Security Now the
Biden Administration with the uh malady
yeah
and that we not only that the FBI paid
Twitter three and a half million dollars
to censored American citizens what do
you think will happen with that
everything you've said is 100 true and
we're learning more and more about it
every day thanks to uh Elon Musk and
Matt taibi and Barry Weiss
um and I hate to say but I think nothing
will happen
I think nothing will happen now if I had
a choice in this I would say there have
to be prosecutions this is clearly a
First Amendment yeah first amendment
constitutional violation right America
had their constitutional rights to
freedom of speech uh uh curtailed at the
insistence of the FBI which is a
governmental entity so clearly
constitutional crimes were committed and
I think that I think that nobody cares
yeah no well I'll tell you what we
conservatives and Republicans we care we
care a lot and we're not happy
yeah
it's important that the information is
coming out to that it to expose the fact
that on every substantive issue that was
in front of the U.S government the U.S
government was an active uh
collaboration with social media to lie
to the American public
the the reality is we have a nation now
founded upon lie after lie after lie
it's being exposed but you know it goes
back to our earlier conversation about
the lack of accountability nobody's
being called on the carpet and held
accountable for it because there are too
many monied interests in this that are
profiting from it you know but they're
making money you know for the FBI
personnel man they got a golden
parachute when they landed at Twitter
and top jobs that's uh you know uh yeah
80 80 FBI agents tasked with nothing but
looking for troublemakers
and unfortunately Gonzalo got caught in
that web but um I'll tell you what if
you send emails to like Twitter support
and say hey can I get my account back
that is what's working for people from
solo and I've been tweeting it out and
tweeting it out so yeah okay that's true
Dixon was reinstated
yeah
okay and hey I think even Scott Ritter
got put back on so you've got to get on
it okay Susie Hugh thank you so much for
being on oh you're welcome and it's good
to see you again all right bye-bye bye
yeah uh yeah because the whole Twitter
thing yeah because the lists that are
coming out and also what's obvious to me
is that see once you hire a bunch of
people to start censoring them you
censor these people and then you start
centering more and more and more to
Justify Your Existence until you censor
everybody until there's nobody left
basically and so it's just absurd and
the fact is that these social media
platforms have de facto become the
Public Square and so you really are
censoring the people uh and this notion
that oh it's a private company they can
do whatever they want
you know that's actually not true I mean
you you can't censor people on the phone
company and and say oh we don't like
your your conversations on the phone so
we're gonna de-platform you and not let
you have a cell phone or a landline I
mean it doesn't work that way and so the
thing is I find it deeply disturbing but
unfortunately I think that John you're
correct
they aren't going to do a goddamn thing
at the end of the day I mean I don't
think they will
yeah
Jesus Christ well I think the only thing
that will be done is what elon's doing
right now eliminating the bots off the
off the platform exposing the
malfeasance and it'll make it a little
more difficult for them to use Twitter
going forward but hey they still have
Facebook
and yeah yeah they certainly do
especially now that Facebook is
completely tanking because they made the
wrong bets but uh uh yeah uh
oh it's it's something there is this
conspiracy theory rumor whatever that
Elon Musk is like CIA or that he's
connected I'm throwing this out there
you know it's not something that I don't
really use a sleepover I I don't think
he's CIA I think it's more overt than
that the guy's got hundreds of millions
of dollars of contracts with the CIA
and with the NSA and the whole National
Security establishment so I mean he's
got a vested interest in making sure
that the CIA is comfortable with
whatever it is he does
how does he have business relationships
with the CIA by the way and then uh
Cloud uh cloud computing cloud computing
yeah okay yeah just we're talking about
Elon Musk right because yeah yeah sure
oh yeah yeah yeah he's a he's a serious
uh National Security contractor
hello
oh okay
go ahead dollar well I just say but it
appears he has the advantage that the
government needs him more than he needs
the government good point for he's got
some freedom to basically you know so if
they don't want to use a fund I'll cut
you off like he could he could shut down
the Ukrainian military tomorrow turn off
starlink they're done
well the Russians have done a pretty
good job of that already yes from what I
understand the Russians have really
clipped uh Star Lincoln it's not as
functioning as it used to be and
attorney and that was something that I
wanted to bring you guys to because
um you know we were talking about like
there were no weapons of mass
destruction in Iraq but since the
administration the Bush Administration
continued after this Revelation there
were no consequences now it's very clear
that the situation in uh uh Ukraine is
deteriorating and so far as the
zelensity regimes
um military is concerned it's really
just a meat grinder that is the major
battle that is taking place here and so
I want to ask you you know eventually
the the the the zlonski regime is going
to collapse this is sort of like
inevitable and so the question becomes
you know once that collapse happens will
there be any effects insofar as the
intelligence Community or do you think
that just the momentum and they'll just
keep on rolling on and
I mean
will there ever be accountability I
suppose is what I'm asking will there
ever be you know something that the
failure is so colossal that they they
have to stand still and take the the
justly deserved beating for their
failures will that moment happen or do
you think that they'll be able to slide
away from everything even the mess that
is being left here in Ukraine
yeah I I think I think they will uh try
to blame it on Biden and uh to ignore
any any accusation that they were
responsible or played any role in this
uh yeah I mean it is going to happen uh
but the you know the the bureaucratic
inertia I can't emphasize enough that
the the size of this monster because it
employs all these people and all these
different hierarchies as long as they're
drawing a paycheck and they show up to
work and you don't rock the boat hey you
live to survive another day and those uh
uh the the sad truth about this is
Whoever has been leading this effort
they'll probably get promoted
reward it yeah they probably will are we
gonna have a Victoria Newland as the new
vice president or something like that
God oh my God you know you wish
something would something would bring an
end to these neocons I mean they've been
that they are consistently wrong
and yeah yeah
and for 25 years yeah it's just
empathetic but anyway look we've been
going on for about an hour and a half uh
it's been a delightful conversation but
I want to drive to a close because you
know always leave on top that that's my
my motto you know there you go Long Life
Is Knowing When It's Time to Go and so I
want to thank Larry and I want to thank
John and uh guys stick around a little
bit we'll we'll just uh just chat a
little bit
um chat do me a favor and if you enjoyed
the show hit a plus one if you hated it
or didn't like either of my guess or me
hit a zero so you know we can get like
instant democracy and and we can know if
if people liked it or not plus one if
you liked it zero if you hated it uh and
there we go with a bunch of plus ones
thank you so much Chad and I hope you
enjoyed the show gentlemen it's as
always a pleasure to have you both on
it's just so much fun and uh yeah
everybody chat I'll catch you next time
take it easy